Good גוט מועד, Gut Moed, good ערב יום טוב, Erev Yom Tov,
good fifth day of the עומר. Omer. We pick up today דף
פה Daf Peh Hey
and we pick up near the bottom of פד עמוד ב. Peh
Dalet Amud Bet.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel,
okay, literally the last line, last four words of the line. Okay,
so we've dealt with one position in the name of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan that if you're in a סימטא Simta and you measure
out the food or you take the food yourself and you put
it in front of the buyer on the סימטא, Simta, that would
constitute a קניין, Kinyan, although that was challenged and questioned and in
the end the גמרא Gemara said that it only meant when you
put it in his bag. Okay, so now for today we're actually
going to focus very much on this קניין Kinyan of something in
the bag of the buyer, putting it in the כלי, Kli, it's
like it's on his property, so essentially it's not a separate קניין
כלי, Kinyan Kli, but it's sort of like a קניין חצר. Kinyan
Chatzer. My vessel is like my mini חצר, Chatzer, like you put
it on top of my donkey, it would be the same, okay,
or somewhat the same. The question though is that if my vessel
is in your yard, you're the seller, it's in your store, how
can we say it's in my חצר Chatzer when it's in your
חצר? Chatzer? Right, it's my bag in your store. So that's כלו
של קונה ברשות מוכר. Kelo shel koneh birshut mocher.
Now, a קניין כלי Kinyan Kli certainly works if it's in a
סימטא Simta or חצר של שניהם, Chatzer shel shneihem, in an alley
where you have the right to put your vessels down. So it's
in my vessel, it's in my possession, I have a right to
have my vessel here, so that's where it works. It doesn't work,
at least we've said so far, in a רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim
because you have no right to put your vessels down. The interesting
question is what about רשות המוכר? Reshut Hamocher? Because in רשות המוכר,
Reshut Hamocher, it's my store, I let you put your bag down
while I'm putting the apples into your bag. You have a right
to put your bags down in my store. But at the end
of the day, it's my store and I'm the one that's currently
in possession of the apples. So how much when it's in my
store but in your bag in my store, has it left my
possession or
not? Okay, and that's the question we're going to raise. רב Rav
and שמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, Shmuel d'amri taveihu, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
both say top of פה עמוד א: Peh Hey Amud Aleph: כלו
של אדם קונה לו בכל מקום, Kelo shel adam koneh lo b'chol
makom, your vessels acquire for you anywhere,
חוץ מרשות הרבים, chutz mirshut harabim, except in a רשות הרבים Reshut
Harabim because you don't even have a right to put your bags
down in רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabim. But it's presumably that would include
a רשות המוכר, Reshut Hamocher, okay, which we're going to see. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש דאמרי תרוייהו, Reish Lakish d'amri taveihu,
now the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael position here is: אפילו ברשות הרבים,
Afilu birshut harabim, even in the public domain. So it seems like
there's that debate. As long as it's, you know, it doesn't matter
how much you're sure shouldn't be putting your bag down, it's in
your bag and therefore you're קונה. Koneh. So אמר רב פפא, Amar
Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa said: לא פליגי, Lo peligi,
they don't really disagree. כאן ברשות הרבים כאן בסימטא. Kan birshut harabim
kan besimta.
When רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel say it doesn't work in רשות
הרבים, Reshut Harabim, they meant רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim literally. Doesn't work
in רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabim. When רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish said it does work in רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabim,
they didn't mean it literally. They meant in a סימטא, Simta, in
a side alley, not in a real public domain. By public domain
they meant a non-private domain. Okay, wait, let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. מיתיבי, Metivei, ואמאי קרי ליה v'amai karlei רשות הרבים? Reshut
Harabim? So if it doesn't, so why do they call it רשות
הרבים? Reshut Harabim? שאינו רשות היחיד, She'eino reshut hayachid, it means it's
non-private. Okay, now, meaning even if it's not in a רשות היחיד,
Reshut Hayachid, in a domain that, you know, is the
purchaser's himself, or maybe the seller's himself, we'll have to see, you
know, maybe that would be, I don't know, somehow more obvious. But
even if it's in a side alley that works. But in a
real רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabim, the claim here is nobody disagrees, that
real רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim does not work. If you're not allowed
to leave your bags down in רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabim, you can't
say your bags are קונה Koneh for you. Yes, רב דוב, Rav
Dov, what did you want to say?
You say no, literally רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabim, but you have a
חלק Chelek in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Oh, there you go. Okay. It might be, but that חלק Chelek
might not allow you to keep your bags down. But it is
interesting to wonder whether this בבל-ארץ ישראל difference might have something to
do with how רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim was used in בבל Bavel
and ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael I was wondering that. Okay, so that's
anyway this question. Is there a real position of that כלו Kelo
works even in a רשות הרבים? Reshut Harabim? So let's take a
look. The גמרא Gemara says like this: הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami
mistabra, it makes sense to think that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was
not saying that it really works in a רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabim.
דאמר רבי אבא אמר רבי יוחנן: D'amar Rebbe Abba Amar Rebbe Yochanan:
כלו של אדם קונה לו בכל מקום שיש לו רשות להניחו, Kelo
shel adam koneh lo b'chol makom sheyesh lo reshut lehanicho, that your
כלו Kelo are קונה Koneh wherever you have a right to put
your vessels down. If you have your right to leave your bag
there, then that's your space right now and therefore if it's in
your bag, you're קונה, Koneh, because now it's like your domain in
your space. But if you don't have a right to put it
down, you can't claim that as your space and something you're under
control over. So therefore it doesn't doesn't work where you don't have
a right to put it down. יש לו רשות yesh lo reshus
אין, in, if you have רשות reshus it works. אין לו רשות
ein lo reshus לא, lo, and it's not, not. So presumably רשות
הרבים reshus harabim you don't have the right. שמע מינה. shma mina.
So from there we can infer it does not work in רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim. But of course that's the question: what is the
reality of רשות הרבים? reshus harabim? And again, the fact that it's
a difference between בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. does make
you sort of wonder, maybe there were some real differences there. But
anyway, the גמרא Gemara is saying at least with רשות הרבים reshus
harabim as it understands it, it's you know, they want to claim
that everybody agrees it does not work because you don't have a
right to keep your bags there on the ground.
Blah blah blah.
Yeah, you can still do הגבהה.
hagbahah. Yes. So what if you're carrying your bag?
Yes, so that's different. So carrying your bag is essentially like הגבהה,
hagbahah, it's lifted. But there's an interesting question of הגבהה: hagbahah: does
it require the act of lifting or is it just being suspended?
Also how high is it lifted? There's also another, we'll see a
little bit about that in a minute when we turn the page.
There's also another thing that's sort of like that it's not called
this in the גמרא, Gemara, but the אחרונים Acharonim call this like
a קנין יד. kinyan yad. Like if you put something in my
hand, right? Am I קונה koneh it because of הגבהה hagbahah or
I'm קונה koneh because it's like on my person? Now you can't
say, oh well, it's like a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. Wait wait,
if a חצר chatzer according to some opinions works only because חצר
chatzer is משום יד, mishum yad, like your חצר chatzer is an
extension of my person, right? So like it should certainly work if
it's on my body myself, that's the most that I it's on
you know, I'm in control of it, right? So therefore, so it
could be that right, if you're holding a bag and you're holding
it off the ground, it's like it's an extension of you, it's
like it's directly on your body. But if it's in your bag
that's on the ground that you're not sort of suspending, that's the
question. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, תא
שמע. ta shema. So now we're going to try to try to
see if we can prove this question of whether it works in
רשות הרבים reshus harabim כליו. kelav. ארבע מידות במוכרין: arbah middos bemochrin:
there are four categories in transactions. Again, like our משנה, Mishnah, four
categories. Except our משנה, Mishnah, the previous משנה Mishnah talked about when
can you sort of cancel the sale because you got the wrong
item. But anyway, here it's talking about four different types of scenarios
in which various קניינים kinyanim work. Now there's a question: how is
this four being divided? But let's just read what these scenarios are
and then we'll worry about what exactly are the four. Okay.
עד שלא נתמלא המידה למוכר, ad shelo nismaila hamiddah lamocher, משנתמלא המידה
ללוקח. mishenismaila hamiddah lalokeach. So there you are, I am going into
Michael's store and I'm buying
some flour, three cups of flour. Michael's got this big, you know,
measuring vessel. He's filling it up. He measures out three cups. So
before that three-cup line gets hit, it's still Michael's flour. Once it
hits that three-cup line, it's my flour. Now what sense does that
mean?
You know that you want the three cups.
Yeah, I ordered three cups, and you're filling up this vessel, right?
And then as once it hits the marking that's the amount that
I'm buying, then it's mine. Now what קנין kinyan did I just
do? So the real question is, well, whose measuring vessel is it?
So what the גמרא Gemara is going to say about this to
make sense of if it's Michael's, why should getting it to the
right line mean that it becomes mine? And if it's mine, well,
so one easy way to explain it is it's my vessel. But
since it's not yet at the amount that I've ordered, I don't
have גמירת דעת gemiras da'as to be קונה koneh until it's the
full amount. That would be one way of explaining it.
Okay. Now but I can have גמירת דעת gemiras da'as all along
the way.
Maybe, right, but at least you could explain it that way. The
way the גמרא Gemara explains it is is that we both borrowed
a third party's vessel. Okay, I said, 'Michael, sell me some flour.'
He says, 'Sure.' He says, 'Oh wait, shoot, I don't have my
measuring vessel here. You know, hey Chanan, can we borrow your vessel?'
'Sure, here, go borrow.' So since Chanan is lending it to the
two of us for the sake of the transaction, the argument is
that it belongs, he's lending it to Michael as long as Michael
needs it. Michael needs it until he gets the three cups measured
out. And then he's letting me use it for as long as
I need it, which is like to pour it into my, into
my sack. So therefore, as soon as Michael is done measuring it
out, then it becomes mine. It's now, you know, now it's lent
to me and now I'm קונה koneh because it's my כלי. kli.
That's the way the גמרא Gemara explains it. Okay. An alternative way
could have just been that it's my כלי kli all along and
the sale is final once it's the full amount and then it's
in my כלי. kli. But anyway, that's case number one. עד שלא
נתמלא המידה למוכר, ad shelo nismaila hamiddah lamocher, before it gets filled
to the amount, it still belongs to the seller. You can back
out. You can back out, or either of us can back
out. Okay. משנתמלא המידה, mishenismaila hamiddah, once it's filled to the amount
that's being purchased, ללוקח, lalokeach, it's the buyer's. במה דברים אמורים במידה
שאינה של שניהם. bameh devarim amurim bemiddah she'einah shel shenehem. Oh, it's
not the גמרא. Gemara. Ha! There it is right here in the
ברייתא, Beraisa, excuse me. Okay. It does not belong to either of
them, meaning it belongs to a third party and they borrowed it.
Right, so it's exactly what I said, except it's right here in
the ברייתא. Beraisa. Okay, so they borrowed it from a third party
and therefore the logic, the גמרא Gemara explains the logic behind it.
The logic is is that since it doesn't belong to either of
us and we're both borrowing it, it's Michael's כלי kli until he's
done measuring it and then I have the right to use it
after he's done measuring it and then I'm קונה koneh with a
קנין כלי. kinyan kli. Okay. So that's when it's borrowed from a
third party. משנתמלא המידה... במה דברים אמורים במידה שאינה של שניהם אבל
אם הייתה מידה של אחד מהם ראשון ראשון קנה. mishenismaila hamiddah... bameh
devarim amurim bemiddah she'einah shel shenehem aval im haysah middah shel achad
mehem rishon rishon kanah. But if it belongs to one of them,
ראשון ראשון קנה. rishon rishon kanah. But if it belongs to one
of them, then... And every bit of flour that's poured into it,
you're קונה koneh it automatically. Now what does that mean? Like if
it belongs to me, I understand why I'm buying flour, I'm buying
three cups, but okay, up to three cups, as soon as the
first amounts come in, I'm buying, that's mine as well, right? It
ends by three cups, but that's as much as I'm buying. So
if it's mine, we understand why I'm קונה, koneh, but why if
it's Michael's, what does it mean ראשון ראשון קנה? rishon rishon kanah?
So if you take a case in a store. Right.
So if you take a look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, he says
right before the line gets the widest, ראשון ראשון, rishon rishon, he
says שנותנים לתוך המידה קנה בעל המידה שאם המידה של מוכר אף
על פי שנתמלא המידה הרי היא של מוכר ולא קנה לוקח. she-notnim
l'toch ha-midah kanah ba'al ha-midah she-im ha-midah shel mocher af al pi
she-nitmala ha-midah harei hi shel mocher v'lo kanah loke'ach. So it's a
strange use of the word קנה. kanah. קנה kanah doesn't mean the
transaction is affected, קנה kanah means it's in the possession of the
person whose vessel it is. Okay, so if it's Michael's vessel, it
completely remains in his possession even after it's filled up, because okay,
it's the full three cups, but it's still Michael's vessel. I haven't
done a קנין kinyan on it. So קנה kanah here doesn't mean
I'm קונה, koneh, it means it remains it's in the possession of
the person whose vessel it is. Okay.
So just kind of like being still on the shelf.
Exactly. Where if it's my vessel, every bit he's pouring is mine
because I'm buying a full three cups, so I'm also buying less
than the three cups as well and therefore every bit is mine.
So if it belongs to Michael, it's all there's no קנין kinyan
until I do something else. If it belongs to me, every bit
that hits the vessel is קונה. koneh. If it belongs to a
third party and we're borrowing it, then it's Michael's until it's filled
and after it's filled it's mine, so only when it's filled then
it becomes mine, then that's a קנין kinyan then I own it.
Okay, that's that case. ראשון ראשון. rishon rishon. במה דברים אמורים? bamei
devarim amurim? Now, all of this thing is where basically the bottom
line is the principle here works is that when it's my vessel,
I'm קונה koneh it. So now this is getting to the heart
of it. Where does my vessel work? Are we in Michael's store?
Is my vessel working in רשות מוכר? reshus mocher? Are we in
a רשות הרבים? reshus ha-rabim? Right, because you understand all these different
cases were just different scenarios under which it becomes my vessel and
then I'm קונה. koneh. So what's the location of this vessel?
That would why that should also work like I'm in your store.
Right. And you put something from the store in my pocket.
Exactly. Exactly. In my bag.
Still is a question whether I've been קונה koneh or not?
Well, pocket it might be like I said, that's like גוף, guf,
that's like יד, yad, but let's say my shopping bag. I come
in with my own canvas shopping bag, I'm a conscientious consumer, I
don't like you giving me all that plastic stuff, okay, so I
come in with my own shopping bag and you put it in
my shopping bag. Okay, so that's the same question, that's כלים. kelim.
Okay, so here we have different variations of when it becomes my
כלי, kli, but where are we? So במה דברים אמורים? bamei devarim
amurim? Where's it talking about? במה דברים אמורים ברשות הרבים ובחצר שאינה
של שניהם. bamei devarim amurim bi-reshus ha-rabim u-ve-chatzer she-eina shel sheneihem. Wow.
So we're in a רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim or we're in somebody's
place that neither and רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim exactly, it's a quiet
day in רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, you always know, or we're in
a חצר chatzer that neither of us have a right to be
there. Now does it mean that we're trespassing? Maybe we have a
right to be there but we don't have a right to be
putting down our bags and our flour there or whatever. So this
is sort of saying that even if you don't have a right
to put your vessels there, it works, קנין כלי kinyan kli works.
Okay? This is like presumably רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש,
Reish Lakish, like the literal meaning of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rabbi
Yochanan v'Reish Lakish. ובחצר שאינה של שניהם, u-ve-chatzer she-eina shel sheneihem, אבל
ברשות מוכר לא קנה. aval bi-reshus mocher lo kanah. If we're in
Michael's רשות, reshus, and was I the buyer here? Yeah, I was
the buyer, so Michael's store, we're in Michael's store, it does not
work a קנין כלי kinyan kli עד שיגביהנה, ad she-yigbihennah, you have
to lift it up, או עד שיוציאנה מרשותו o ad she-yotzi'ennah me-reshuto
or take it out of his store. Okay, because הגבהה hagbahah works
בכל מקום. be-chol makom. So here we're saying that this is like
the opposite of what the גמרא Gemara assumes. The גמרא Gemara generally
assumes that קנין כלי kinyan kli definitely does not work in רשות
הרבים reshus ha-rabim because you don't have any right to put it
there. It might work in רשות מוכר reshus mocher because Michael's letting
me put my bag down to put the apples in my bag.
On the other hand, you can argue that even though I have
the right to put my bag down, it's still Michael's store and
Michael's apples, so it hasn't really left his control. So the גמרא
Gemara has a question of כלי ברשות מוכר, kli bi-reshus mocher, we're
going to get to that next. But the גמרא Gemara seems to
take for granted that כלי kli should not work in רשות הרבים
reshus ha-rabim because I don't have a right to put my vessels
down. This ברייתא, braisa, this תוספתא Tosefta is saying the opposite. It's
saying that the כלי kli works in רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim but
it doesn't work in רשות מוכר. reshus mocher. And you could understand
that position as well, right? Maybe I shouldn't be putting my bag
down but right now it's in my bag and it's out of
Michael's control and it's in my control, so therefore it's mine. But
in Michael's store, it always remains under his control as long as
we're still within the store. Okay, so that's the position of this
תוספתא Tosefta which is the exact sort of opposite of the assumptions
of the גמרא. Gemara. So we're going to sort of see about
how to make it all work. Okay, that's stage number one. כלי
kli works in רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim but it doesn't work in
רשות מוכר. reshus mocher. And in רשות המוכר Reshus HaMocher you have
to actually do הגבהה Hagbahah or take it out of the store,
עד שיוציאנו מרשותו, ad sheyotzienu mereshuto, presumably into a סמטא Simta or
like some type of a משיכה Meshichah if you're taking it out
of the store. ברשות לוקח, Bi-reshut loke'ach, now let's say it's actually
we're doing the transaction in my רשות. reshus. Michael's a door-to-door salesman
and I invite him in and then he measures out some apples
there. So in that case, כיון שקבל עליו מוכר קנה לוקח, kivan
she-kibel alav mocher kanah loke'ach, as soon as we've agreed upon it,
okay, yes, sell it, whatever, sure, okay, great, so it's done. So
now, I mean, it's in my domain, I'm קונה koneh with the
קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So Charlie's saying, "Wow," not because he's never
heard of a קנין חצר kinyan chatzer before, but because it's like
one thing if we're not in my yard and I say, "Deliver
it," and when you deliver it and put it in your yard,
there's a concrete moment in time where we say, "Ah, now he's
קונה," koneh, it was put in his yard. But if Charlie enters
in with his apples into my house, like when exactly did we
say? Like we were discussing the price of, "Oh, that sounds good."
Does "sounds good" mean yes or does it not mean yes? Right?
So it's like the whole point of a קנין kinyan is to
identify the concrete moment where the transaction takes place, right? And I
agree with you, saying
קבל עליו kibel alav is not a clear, concrete moment. You'd generally
look for a specific concrete action.
He hasn't even given it to you yet.
Right, well, they're lying on the floor something, and that's another interesting
question. Let's say they're in Charlie's bags. So we've been discussing if
my כלים kelim work, right, if the כלים kelim of the purchaser
work
in the store of the
seller.
Does if it's in the yard of the purchaser, but in the
כלים kelim of the seller, does that prevent my yard from being
קונה? koneh? Right? It's the same, it's the mirror image, so we're
going to get to that. This is after the delivery.
Yes, but that's what we said. If I already bought it, if
we already agreed and then it's delivered, you could say the act
of putting it in my yard is the act of the קנין.
kinyan. But if Charlie comes in with his fruit and we're discussing
the price and how much or whatever, says, "Oh yeah, that sounds
good, I think so, sure, fine, whatever," then it says, oh, as
soon as we've agreed it works. Well, when's that exact moment that
we've agreed? It's not a concrete act, right? So that's a little,
we understand that there's a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer.
Is there a difference whose כלי kli it is?
So here it's not clear. So that's going to be a question
also, which is if it's still in Charlie's כלי, kli, does קנין
חצר kinyan chatzer still work? But what we're pointing out now is
that this is the whole point about this is to remove ambiguity,
to identify a concrete act in which the transaction takes place. If
they're already in my yard and then there's an agreement and a
meeting of minds or whatever, you understand why all the requirements are
met, but it creates ambiguity. Anyway, that's the case of רשות לוקח.
reshus loke'ach. And
now ברשות הלה המופקדים אצלו, bi-reshut hala hamufkadim etzlo, if
let's say, basically, Michael is keeping
his apples
in David's warehouse, okay? So that's מופקדים אצלו, mufkadim etzlo, the apples
are being kept in David's warehouse. And then I buy ten bushels
of apples from Michael. Okay, so can I now use David's warehouse
to be a temporary קנין חצר kinyan chatzer for me? Okay, so
in that case, ברשות הלה המופקדים אצלו bi-reshut hala hamufkadim etzlo לא
קנה, lo kanah, I'm not קונה koneh עד שקבל עליו. ad she-kibel
alav.
David basically accepts upon himself that now we'll designate that space for
you, Dov. Or basically, Dov,
Michael's apples are in my space, Michael hasn't rented that space. If
Michael rented that space, it's Michael's space. Okay, you're just being a
nice guy and keeping Michael's apples in your house. So if you
say, "Okay, now, David, I will," "Now, Dov, I will hold those
apples for you instead of for Michael," then that
works, או עד שישכור מקומן, o ad she-yischar mekomon, or I can
rent the space from you. Now, that's so. Why does that have
to be a third party? Why can't we say that they were
in Michael's house? Because here's the thing. If they're in Michael's house,
they're like, let's say, here, here are the apples. Okay? They're in
Michael's house. Let's say that's similar to being in Michael's hand. Here,
Michael, put them in your hand. Okay? Michael's holding on to those
apples and selling it to me. So now Michael says, "Oh, it's
okay, Dov, now I'm going to hold on to them for you."
It's like, huh? How is that קונה? koneh? It's not my חצר,
chatzer, I don't own it, I haven't rented it. He's saying he's
holding it for me; he's the seller. That doesn't work. But let's
say now these apples are being held by David. Here, David, hold...
The apples. Okay. So now, so now Michael says, "Okay, so I'm
going to sell you Dov the apples." So David says, "Fine, I'm
now holding those apples for Dov." So what's that like? That's basically
like he is being קונה koneh them, right, for me. It's like
that's the classic example of sort of saying like, you know how
ever like if you have to make a like a עירוב eiruv
or whatever, you say here, here's the box of מצה, matzah, be
קונה koneh for everybody in the town. Or you want to get
out of having to give a gift on שבת, Shabbos, so you
say to somebody here Michael, you know, I'm going over to Michal's
house for שבת, Shabbos, here's a bottle, it's really not a problem
if they're going to use it on שבת. Shabbos. But whatever. Okay.
I'm going to get a nice book for her kids on, you
know, and whatever, and they might not use it on שבת, Shabbos,
so we have to get rid of the money, so we have
to do the מעשה קנין maise kinyan now. Okay, to do a
קנין kinyan for Michal right now. So you can do that. זכין
לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin l'adam shelo befanav, right?
So David, who's holding on to the apples for Michael, right, they're
in his house, he is being זוכה zocheh now, he's using his
חצר, chatzer, like he's using his יד yad to be זוכה zocheh
those apples for me. So he can do it because he's a
third party. But you can't say, "Okay, I'm going to take it
from my right hand, my left hand, and put it into my
right hand and now I'm זוכה." zocheh. You need a a
another party no, but you need somebody other than the seller. Somebody
to represent the other side. So therefore if it's in now Michael
could I could do שכירות מקום schirus makom from Michael. That I
could do because then it becomes my יד. yad. But this case
of not even without a שכירות, schirus, just saying I am now
holding it for the buyer, can only work if it's a third
party. Cannot work if it's the seller. And that's why we have
this other case. So for תוספות, Tosafos, there's a whole question because
we said four מדות, middos, what are the four מדות? middos? So
תוספות Tosafos says the four מדות middos are the four different domains.
The four different domains are רשות הרבים reshus harabbim where קנין כלי
kinyan kli works according to this תוספתא, Tosefta,
רשות מוכר reshus mocher where קנין כלי kinyan kli does not work
and only הגבהה hagbahah works. Okay. רשות לוקח reshus lokeiach where it
works automatically. Okay. And רשות reshus of a of a third party.
So that seems obvious. Those are the four things. רשב"ם Rashbam doesn't
like it because the רשב"ם Rashbam says, "I don't get it," says
the רשב"ם, Rashbam, "the same קנינים kinyanim that work in רשות מוכר
reshus mocher work in רשות reshus of the third party. If I'm
in Michael's domain, I could do הגבהה hagbahah or take it out
of his domain into like a סמטא, simta, well, that's true if
it's in David's house as well. If it's in the third party.
If I'm in David's house, I can do שכירות, schirus, well, I
can do שכירות schirus from Michael as well." So he says they're
all the same, so those aren't really separate domains. But תוספות Tosafos
says no, they are separate for this one reason. This example we
gave about without שכירות, schirus, that it's sufficient that David just says
he's going to now hold it for me. And that would not
work that only works in the hands of a third party, it
doesn't work in Michael's hands. So those are the four different domains.
What's relevant for us immediately is that that כלי kli works in
a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and not רשות מוכר, reshus mocher, which
is almost the exact opposite of the assumptions of the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, yes.
So, could I make a deal with David from the very beginning
saying, "Look, you're you're my warehouse guy." Right. "Forget about Dov, forget
whatever it is, you know..."
If you actually rented the space from David, that's not the case.
If... "No, no, but let's say like listen, you know, I'm a
seller. I'm not going to have you there every time and I
can't have you be Dov, or Michal, or whatever, right?
You're indifferent to whoever my purchaser is. Just have him in mind
whenever I do it, you're your קנין kinyan abstract. You're holding it
for whoever..." Or do I have to know who it is and
say...
Yeah, that's an interesting question. Yeah, it's an interesting question. A type
of a ברירה, breira, meaning he can't be קונה koneh for somebody,
you know,
without being aware of it. But question is can he do like
a ברירה? breira? Can, you know, David sort of say at the
beginning, you put all the apples in his domain, and he says
at the beginning, "I will be קונה koneh these apples for the
person that Michael designates at the time when Michael designates it." Yeah,
I assume like a type of a ברירה breira like that would
sort of work. It wouldn't even be so much of a ברירה
breira because he's not making it work retroactively. He is I mean,
it's sort of like he doesn't know for whom, but it's only
going to work at the time you designate. So at the I
will be doing holding for that person as Michael designates, you could
probably work, yeah. Yeah.
Where does this תוספתא Tosefta start?
תא שמע ארבע מדות במוכרין. Tashma arba middos bemochrin. So this is
just this
is all the way back? What? Doesn't it say דתניא? d'tanya?
Well, no, דתניא d'tanya is what תא שמע... Tashma...
תא שמע, Tashma, דתניא, d'tanya, whatever.
No, no, תא שמע Tashma just starts straight. I don't I don't
know when it says תניא. tanya. תא שמע Tashma often just starts
straight. Okay, so that's anyway. So קתני מיהא katani miha does a
nice big, complicated, you know, sort of multi-faceted תוספתא, Tosefta, but קתני
מיהא katani miha what we see nevertheless for our discussion of כלים
kelim in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, ברשות הרבים ובחצר שאינו של שניהם,
bireshus harabbim u'vchatzer she'eino shel shneihem, that the כלים kelim work in
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim ובחצר שאינו של שניהם. u'vchatzer she'eino shel shneihem.
מאי לאו ברשות הרבים ממש? Mai lav bireshus harabbim mamash? Presumably we
really mean it. Especially because it's backed by the line ובחצר שאינו
של שניהם. u'vchatzer she'eino shel shneihem. So לא סמטא. lo simta. So
just like we reread רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish when they said כלי keli works in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim
to say they didn't literally mean it, they meant a סימטא, simta,
so too yes, the תוספתא Tosefta doesn't mean it, it means a
סימטא. simta. והא דומיא דחצר שאינה של שניהם קתני? ve-ha dumya de-chatzer
she-einah shel shneihem katani? Hard to get out of this one because
you could say רשות הרבים reshut harabbim means not a private domain,
but this is comparing it to a חצר שאינה של שניהם chatzer
she-einah shel shneihem and the line of comparison is you don't have
a right to be putting your vessels down there, right? So sounds
like it's a real רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. מה חצר שאינה של
שניהם נמי דלאו דהאי כולה ולאו דהאי כולה? ma chatzer she-einah shel
shneihem nami de-lav de-hai kulla ve-lav de-hai kulla? It means it's not
a fully private domain, it's not fully one person's and not fully
another person's.
אלא דתרווייהו. ella de-tarveihu. It really means חצר שאינה של שניהם, chatzer
she-einah shel shneihem, you know what it really means? חצר של שניהם.
chatzer shel shneihem. Exactly. It means it means חצר שאינה של אחד
מהם אלא של שניהם. chatzer she-einah shel echad me-hem ella shel shneihem.
So it's a very forced reread of this ברייתא. braita. The ברייתא
braita clearly seems to see that a כלי keli works in רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, which is similar to רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi
Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish seems to be an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael position
that כלים keilim works in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. And presumably
it's not because you have a right to keep things in רשות
הרבים reshut harabbim because it also says חצר שאינה של שניהם. chatzer
she-einah shel shneihem. Presumably it's saying I don't care if you have
a right to put it there or not, once it's not under
the seller's control and it's in your bag, maybe you shouldn't be
leaving your bag in the middle of Times Square, but if it's
in your bag and not in the seller's control, it's yours. That
seems to be the position of the ברייתא, braita, of רבי יוחנן
וריש לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish, of the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
position, which the בבלי Bavli rejects and it rereads all these positions.
Okay. Because
of this position that if you don't have a right to keep
your כלים keilim there, then it's then it's not...
You'd better have a forced reread
exactly, exactly.
You mentioned ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael position, does ירושלמי Yerushalmi agree with
the בבלי? Bavli?
I haven't checked ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Okay. Which I should have. Okay. בעי
מיניה. baei minei. Now, so we're done with that. We've decided in
face of all the evidence, you know what's the story, don't bother
me with the evidence, my mind is made up. In face of
all the evidence, we've decided that כלים keilim do not work in
a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. Now we're onto the next question. בעי
מיניה רב ששת מרב הונא: baei minei Rav Sheshet me-Rav Huna: כלים
שלוקח ברשות מוכר. keilim she-loke'ach bi-reshut mocher. So how about in the
seller's domain? As I said, this is interesting because on the one
hand,
from the תוספתא's Tosefta position, it definitely does not work, right? We
saw that. But here, the בבלי Bavli is more open to this
possibility. On the one hand, the מוכר mocher lets you put your
bags down in his store. On the other hand, it's still under
the seller's control. So כלים שלוקח ברשות מוכר קנה לוקח או לא?
keilim she-loke'ach bi-reshut mocher kana loke'ach o lo? Does it work or
not? אמר ליה תניתוה. amar leh tanituha. We taught it. And here
becomes now some of the questions you were asking about, what if
it's on the person's body or the person's person? זרקו לה לתוך
חיקה. zarko lah le-toch cheikah. So this is a case of גיטין.
gittin. The husband, the wife is standing in the husband's house, so
it's in the husband's domain, and throws the גט get onto the
wife onto his wife's person. Okay. And she catches it in her
skirt or whatever. And we'll see. Now, the first thing to assume
here is the assumption of this גמרא, Gemara, which can be questioned,
is that the act of giving a גט get is the same
as a מעשה קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. The פסוק pasuk says, וכתב לה
ספר כריתת ונתן בידה. ve-chatav lah sefer keritut ve-natan be-yadah. Put it
in her hand. So you might say, put it in her hand,
put it on her person, whatever, that's the act of giving a
גט. get. Who says it has to work from the laws of
הלכות קנינים? hilchot kinyanim? Okay. But the גמרא's Gemara making the assumption
that if it works for גט, get, it works for a מעשה
קנין. ma'aseh kinyan. Okay. And here's the case. So זרקו לה לתוך
חיקה. zarko lah le-toch cheikah. Into her bosom, which really means basically
like it's in her it's in her lap or חיקה. cheikah. Does
it mean bosom or does it mean lap? What? I think lap.
Is that really but is that what the word means? If you
look at the... It means lap and... It does?
Really? Interesting.
Okay.
It seems to go with lap though.
They do? Is that a... I know but I'm just trying to...
Okay, fine, whatever. Is that the tannaic use of the word? Anyway,
anyway, but the רשב"ם Rashbam says it means כלומר על בגדיה שהיא
מלובשת. kelomar al begadeha she-hi melubbeshet. So somehow like falls into her
clothes, okay? So okay, זרקו לה לתוך חיקה. zarko lah le-toch cheikah.
Fine, we'll translate it as lap. Falls into her lap.
Where were we? או לתוך קלתה, o le-toch kaltah, or into her
basket, הרי זו מגורשת. harei zu megureshet. It works. And so our
focus here is maybe less on the lap and more on the
basket, right? Because the lap I had a whole discussion about whether
that's considered on a person might be very different than in a
כלי. keli. What?
קלתה's Kaltah a Greek word.
Okay. But a קלתה kaltah is a basket. Okay. So here you
have it in the קלתה. kaltah. So how what how you going
to explain this?
There's an expression חיק משפחה, cheik mishpacha, like in the folds of
the family. Yes. So it could be like in the... in the
house.
חיבוק. chibbuk.
Okay,
all right, fine. Okay. הרי זו מגורשת. harei zu megureshet. אמר ליה
רב נחמן. amar leh Rav Nachman. So that seems to be a
proof. It looks like, assuming that there's an equation between the act
of giving a גט get and a מעשה קניין, ma'aseh kinyan, it
seems like עם הכלים im hakaylim works. Okay, that's considered to be
on, you know, in that person's domain. Now the comparison might be
not an assumption that you need a מעשה קניין ma'aseh kinyan to
work for for giving of a גט, get, although you might. It
might be the assumption that, what is the logic why it works
when something's in my bag? 'Cause it's considered like I said before
in my חצר. chatzer. Okay, the גמרא gemara even says by a
גט, get, ונתן בידה. venasan beyadah. בידה אין לי אלא בידה חצירה
גגה חצר קפיפה מנין? beyada ein li ela beyada chatzeira gaga chatzer
kefifa minayin? תלמוד לומר ונתן מכל מקום. talmud lomar venasan mikol makom.
So anyway we know by a גט get it works to put
it not only on the woman's person but in the woman's domain
property. So therefore if a כלי kli works 'cause it's considered property,
so here we have a question, my little piece of property, my
little כלי kli in the middle of your store, in the middle
of your house, in the middle of your property, is it considered
my property at that moment? Is it in my property or is
it in your property? So that is a question that has implications
for קניינים, kinyanim, but it could also have implications for גיטין gittin
even if a גט get is not based on a normal מעשה
קניין, ma'aseh kinyan, it still they all have to satisfy the same
requirement: whose property is it on? Is it on the property, is
it considered to be in the property of the person who owns
the bag, or is it considered to be in the property of
the person who owns the domain? Okay, and therefore that will determine
if you're קונה koneh and that will determine if you put it
in the woman's property to work for an act of giving a
גט. get. Okay, so that's the question here and here we see
that if it's in the woman's basket even if it's in the
man's property, it's considered to be in the woman's property and therefore
if it works for גט get it should work for קניינים. kinyanim.
So that's the proof. So אמר ליה רב נחמן, amar leh rav
nachman, so רב נחמן rav nachman said
so back, מאי טעמא פשיט לה מהא, mai ta'ama pashistah meihahi, whoever
gave this answer, I guess רב הונא rav huna gave this answer
to רב ששת rav sheshet and then רב נחמן rav nachman said
מאי טעמא פשיט לה מהא, mai ta'ama pashistah meihahi, why did you
try to determine the you know the the answer the question from
that from that teaching? דמחלה מאה וכלי באוכלא, demachla mei'ah uchli be'uchla,
they
served being that a hundred times with a measuring vessel, so that's
a phrase which means like they they completely knocked that proof down
because this was raised over in גיטין gittin as well this question,
does this prove that כליו של אדם קונה לו ברשות מוכר? keilav
shel adam koneh lo bereshut mocher? דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, de'amar
rav yehuda amar shmuel, 'cause they gave a lot of different explanations
to that: פשיטא כלתה תלויה בה. pashitah kalsah teluyah bah.
If only if it was suspended on her body, there you have
it, you see Rebbe Dov? So if you're holding onto the bag
and it's not on the ground and it's sort of you've got
it around your neck or you're holding onto it, then it's like
it's on you, then it's either הגבהה hagbah or it's like it's
on your body, that's a different story. That's not just a קניין
כלי. kinyan kli. Okay, ריש לקיש אמר קשורה אף על פי שאינה
תלויה בה. reish lakish amar keshurah af al pi she'eina teluyah bah.
Now that's more interesting because Dov I think you asked yesterday, what
if you're holding your bag and the bag is on the ground?
So here ריש לקיש reish lakish says not exactly holding, but if
the bag is tied to your person and it's on sitting on
the ground, that might be the same as being on your person.
Okay, so there are times in which if you're holding the bag,
it's on your person, it's tied to you, it's like it's on
your person, but that's very different than being in the כלי kli
okay
if it is what do you call it if the כלי kli
is is on the ground and you're not holding it and it's
not suspended from you. Now the רשב"ם rashbam says תלויה בה teluyah
bah so if you look at the רשב"ם rashbam he says ואינה
נגררת בקרקע ולהכי קני לה כלתה דדמי להגבהה דקניא בכל מקום. ve'eina
niggeres bakarka ulkach koneh lah kalsah dedami lahagbah shekoneh bechol makom. Okay,
so he says it's similar to הגבהה hagbah but I do want
to say that some have said you know that certainly the case
of קשורה keshurah as opposed to the case of תלויה, teluyah, it
might be a case of הגבהה hagbah it might be like what's
called a קניין יד. kinyan yad. It's just on your person, that
might be sufficient because the basic question here is not from the
first part of חיקה, cheikah, it's from the second part of כלתה.
kalsah. If it's on your person then that always works wherever you
are. Like what's that line, wherever you go there you are. So
even if you're in רשות מוכר reshut mocher or the woman is
in רשות בעל, reshut ba'al, okay, it's still her person. On your
person that's always giving it to you. So do these things work
when it's suspended or when it's tied because of a type of
הגבהה hagbah or do they work because then it's like directly on
the person? But our question is on the כלי kli that's not
connected to you. Does that work? Okay, רב אדא
בר אהבה אמר כגון שהייתה כלתה מונחת לה בין ירכותיה. rav adda
bar ahava amar kegon shehayetah kalsah munachas lah bein yarkhoteha. It's like
she was sitting down and between you know and and you know
and like and her basket like you know you're knitting or whatever
and you're sitting down and that basket is between her legs. Now
that doesn't answer it. Okay? Does that make it it's on her
person? It's not like it's tied, it's not like it's suspended, she's
surrounding it, but that should be a standard question of a קניין
כלי. kinyan kli. So we're going to have to see why that
matters. רב משראשיה בריה דרב אמי אמר כגון שהיה בעלה מוכר כלתות.
rav mesharshaya bereih derav ami amar kegon shehayah ba'alah mocher kalsot. Her
husband sold baskets, which basically means that there was a room filled
with baskets so he's okay for her to put it down. Down
her basket at that moment. Now why does even those last two
they still don't explain it? It's still her basket in her husband's
yard, it's not on her body, it's not suspended, so the גמרא
Gemara says רבי יוחנן אמר מקום חיקה קנוי לה מקום כלתא קנוי
לה. Rabbi Yohanan amar mekom cheika kanuy lah, mekom klatasta kanuy lah.
So just as
she has a right to where her lap is and where her
basket is. So what does this mean? אמר רבא מאי טעמא דרבי
יוחנן? Amar Rava mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yohanan? What's the reason? לפי שאין
אדם מקפיד לא על מקום חיקה ולא על מקום כלתא. L'fi she'ein
adam makpid lo al mekom cheika v'lo al mekom klatasta. A man
doesn't- is not מקפיד, makpid, you know, where his wife wants to
sit and where lap is- I guess that's the lap of the
חיקה cheika is the lap because presumably the case of בין ירכיה,
bein yercheiha, it's sitting like between her legs means she's going to
squat on the ground, he's okay with her using that space and
therefore he's not מקפיד makpid that she uses that space or he's
not מקפיד makpid where she puts down her basket especially if he
sells baskets. Now the funny thing here is, okay, but is that
true? Well the classic כליו של קונה ברשות מוכר kailav shel koneh
b'reshut mocher is that you're not מקפיד makpid that the guy puts
down his bag either, right? So how is that different? It seems
that the difference is that one we're sort of talking about like
ongoing. Like if I'm in a store, right, you can't keep your
bag here, you know, for more than the minute it takes you
to fill it up. It's like there's other customers coming, buddy, get
out of the way, okay? So you only have a very temporary
right to have your bag here, so fundamentally it's my control, my
domain, your bag here is very, you know, is in a very
tenuous way, so we could say it's not קונה. koneh. Whereas my
wife in my house, right, before the process of divorce or whatever,
even though it's my house, technically I own it, right, so you
know, it's in- the deed is in my name, generally she's allowed
to sit in my house. I let her sit here, I let
her put her stuff here, whatever, in sort of an ongoing type
of a way. So since there's that sort of ongoing right to
do that, when her basket is here, it's more like she- it's
full- it's, you know, it's in her domain. Maybe the- if it's
on the piece of ground that she has a right to sit
on, that's not in her domain, that's my domain that I'm letting
her sit on it. But if it's in her basket, right remember,
the idea is the basket is קונה koneh because it's the רשות
reshut of the purchaser or because it's the domain of the wife.
But the question is how much does the fact that the basket
is in my house undermine it from being considered to be in
that person's domain and it's under my domain. So here, if there's
more of an ongoing right that the woman has to have the
basket there, not just temporarily but ongoing, then it's being in her
basket is considered in her domain. So the point is the case
by גיטין gittin is not a proof to the case of כליו
של קונה ברשות מוכר, kailav shel koneh b'reshut mocher, not because גט
get is different than מקח וממכר, mekach u'mimkar, which would have been
an interesting categorical distinction to make, but circumstantially. It's suspended from her,
so it's like הגבהה. hagba'ah. It's tied to her, so it's like
it's on her body. It's a case where she has a general
right to be there in a more ongoing way, and to use
that space in a more ongoing way, not just temporarily, and therefore
being in her basket is considered to be in her domain under
her control. But if you're here in my store for a few
minutes and you have a right for a few minutes to put
your basket down, it still fundamentally under my control and you cannot,
you know, and your- and it might not be קונה. koneh. I'm
wondering in all of this, you know, about what happens about like-
for some reason this is where my head is going- in terms
of like shoplifting, if I sneak something into my bag, can you-
can you actually, like, you know, prosecute me for shoplifting before I've
stepped out of the store, right? So it's like when it's in
my bag and I'm in your store, have I really taken it
or not yet taken it? Right? So it's like a similar type
of a question. Yeah, Charlie, what did you want to say?
It's between- she's sitting down in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim between her
legs, she doesn't really have the right to sit.
Yeah, it's not רשות הרבים reshut harabbim though, it's her husband's domain.
Yeah, that's- that's clearly...
Yeah no, all of this is in her husband's house. That's the
assumption. Okay, so now we haven't proven it from the גיטין gittin
case.
Yes. You're still on the first משנה mishna here? I mean it
listed ארבע מידות במוכרים. arba midot b'mochrim.
Are we still on
the first one or...
Well, we're not focusing on the ברייתא, baraita, we're sort of- we're
using the ברייתא baraita as evidence, but we're raising big questions. So
big question number one is כליו ברשות הרבים. kailav b'reshut harabbim. So
the evidence from the ברייתא baraita was that it works, but we've
rejected that. כליו ברשות הרבים kailav b'reshut harabbim does not work. How
about כליו ברשות מוכר? kailav b'reshut mocher? So now we're trying to
prove that from גיטין gittin and we've rejected that. Now what we
should do is we should turn to the ברייתא baraita because the
ברייתא baraita says it doesn't work ברשות מוכר, b'reshut mocher, okay, which
is what we're going to do in a minute. But we're not
following the lead of the ברייתא, baraita, we're raising questions and we're
drawing on the ברייתא baraita for evidence. Michal, you had a question?
Okay, yes.
I think the קונה koneh wants
the
product, doesn't he?
Yeah, both of them.
Yeah. Now, but the wife, she may reject the divorce.
Right, but that- correct, but what correct, but what you see here
and you see in most cases is is that the... the desire
because a גט get works בעל כרחה. bal karcha. There are two
components to every transaction: there's the דעת, daas, and there normally is
דעת daas of both of them. In the case of a גט,
get, it's the דעת daas of the husband, it's one side and
the act of the קנין. kinyan. So but but the presumably what
constitutes an act of קנין kinyan is not affected by the question
of the דעת. daas. You need the דעת daas and you need
the act of the קנין, kinyan, but you know, they don't but
the fact that in one case it's two people's דעת daas and
in one case it's one דעת daas seems from the גמרא's Gemara's
perspective shouldn't determine how the act of the קנין kinyan is defined
for a קנין. kinyan. Well or as we were saying before, it
might not be the same type of a קנין kinyan but it's
definitely a question of whether it's in her רשות, reshus, whatever it's
defined as being in her רשות. reshus. Okay right. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so we still haven't concluded כליו
של לוקח ברשות מוכר. kelav shel loke’ach b’reshus mocher.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא פשיט ליה מהא. ela pashit lei
me-ha. So fine, let's try to conclude it from this, from our
ברייתא. braisa. ברשות מוכר לא קנה עד שיגביהנו או עד שיוציאנו
מרשותו. b’reshus mocher lo kana ad she’yagbihenu o ad she’yotzienu me’reshuso. Right,
the ברייתא, braisa, the תוספתא tosefta seems very clear, the exact opposite
of where the גמרא Gemara is going. רשות הרבים reshus harabim in
the ברייתא braisa does work, which the גמרא Gemara rejected, the
כליו, kelav, and רשות מוכר reshus mocher doesn't work. So look, here's
the ברייתא, braisa, it doesn't
work. Exactly what we're going to do. So מאי לאו בכליו דלוקח.
mai lav be’kelav de’loke’ach. Are we not talking about even if, since
it says you need הגבהה hagbahah or you need to take it
out, presumably it means that even if it's in your bags, the
bag of the לוקח, loke’ach, you're not
קונה. koneh. לא בכליו דמוכר. lo be’kelav de’mocher. No, what we meant
was when it was in the bags of the מוכר, mocher, but
if it was in the bags of the לוקח loke’ach it would
have worked, which is so bizarre. Then it should have said עד
שיתן לתוך כליו או יגביהנו או יוציאנו. ad she’yiten lesoch kelav o
yagbihenu o yotzienu. Right, the fact anyway but that's the claim. The
circumstances are it was in the seller's כליו, kelav, you know, vessels,
bags. But if it was in the buyer's bags it would have
worked.
Okay, ומדרישא בכליו דמוכר סיפא נמי בכליו דמוכר. u-mide’reisha be’kelav de’mocher seifa
nami be’kelav de’mocher. But says wait one minute.
So we're going to now assume that this ברייתא braisa is taking
for as a default that it's in the seller's bags? The whole
the rest of the ברייתא braisa won't work. Why? What does the
rest of the ברייתא braisa say? אמא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look
at the next line at the other line. ברשות לוקח כיון שקיבל
עליו מוכר קנה לוקח. bi’reshus loke’ach keivan she’kibel alav mocher kana loke’ach.
Okay,
this is what we were doing, right? Charlie brings his apples into
my house, is trying to sell me his apples. It says it
works as soon as we agree because it's in my domain. So
one minute, we're going to assume now that the apples are in
the seller's bags.
דאי בכליו דמוכר אמאי קנה לוקח. de’i be’kelav de’mocher amai kana loke’ach.
But if they're in Charlie's bags, why am I קונה? koneh? Now
let's pause for a moment. Why is the גמרא Gemara here assuming
that if in Charlie's bags in my house I'm not קונה? koneh?
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says and תוספות Tosafos says this is not
the גמרא's Gemara's גמרא Gemara is not committed to that position. What
the גמרא Gemara assumes and this is very important to understand because
this is going to continue is is that it work is that
the two cases are parallel or are equal.
The seller's bags in the buyer's domain and the buyer's bags in
the seller's domain. Now you have to make up your mind. If
it's in X's bag and Y's domain, whose domain is it in?
Is it defined as in the in whose space is it in
to want to think about that? Is it in the space is
it in the domain in the space of the bag or in
the domain in the space of of the larger domain?
If you say the space is going to be קונה koneh and
not the bag, you have to say that the house is going
to be
קונה koneh and not the bag. Exactly. So whatever you answer by
one, the גמרא Gemara is going to assume you have to answer
by the other. Now you could make reasons to say it should
be different, but that's the assumption of the גמרא. Gemara. So here
our argument has been that we're trying to explain the ברייתא. braisa.
The ברייתא braisa in its simple sense says that כליו kelav does
not work in רשות מוכר reshus mocher of the לוקח. loke’ach. But
גמרא Gemara is saying no no no no, if it was the
לוקח's loke’ach's bags it would work. We're only talking about a case
that it's the seller's bags. So if גמרא's Gemara's trying to argue
within the ברייתא braisa that כליו kelav works, that it's considered in
the כליו's kelav's bags, it's considered in the space of the כלי
kli if it's in that bag. So then the גמרא Gemara says
so then how come when Charlie is bringing his bag of apples
into my domain am I קונה koneh it? If if it's in
his bags that should per that should mean it's in his space
and not my space, you gotta be consistent. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says so really and the גמרא's Gemara's right, the simple sense
of the ברייתא braisa is is that it goes by the domain,
not the bags, and that makes the ברייתא braisa read very easy.
If I am buying them in in Charlie's store, I'm not קונה
koneh until I leave the store even if they're in my bags
because they're in his store, goes by the domain. If Charlie brings
his apples into my domain, I'm קונה koneh even though they're in
his bags. So that's the simple read of the ברייתא. braisa. The
simple read of the ברייתא braisa is it goes by the person's
domain, not by the כלים kelim they're in. But the גמרא's Gemara's
saying and if you want to argue it goes by the כלים
kelim and it goes and we're talking about רשות מוכר reshus mocher
then why when they are the apples are in Charlie's bags in
my domain am I קונה? koneh? So let's see what the answer
is. So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי קנה לוקח. amai kana loke’ach.
So the גמרא Gemara says no.
סיפא עסקינן בכלים דלוקח. Seifa askinnan bekelim delokeach. In that case where
Charlie is selling me apples in my domain, they're in my bags.
So the גמרא Gemara says so even though the real difference in
the ברייתא Baraita is whose domain it is, the גמרא Gemara says
what really is going on is whose bags are they in. So
the גמרא Gemara says ומאי פסקא, Umai paska, what how do you
cut that off
meaning who put them in your bags?
Yeah, or something like that. Exactly. He brings yeah something like that.
So where do you get off saying that when in the case
of the store it's in the seller's bags and in the case
of the house of the buyer it's in the buyer's bags? Like
who determines that that's what we're talking about? גמרא Gemara says no,
סתמא דמילתא Stama demilsa בי מוכר מני דמוכר שכיחי Be mocher mani
democher shechichi בי לוקח מני דלוקח שכיחי. Be lokeach mani delokeach shechichi.
If you're in the seller's store, then there are the available bags
are the seller's bags, and if in the buyer's home, the available
bags are the buyer's bags. So anyway, the ברייתא Baraita is very
clear. It's so interesting. The גמרא Gemara is consistently working against the
פשט Pshat of the ברייתא. Baraita. The ברייתא Baraita very clearly says
it does not matter whose bags they're in, it matters whose domain.
If I'm in Charlie's store, I can't be קונה Koneh them presumably
even in my bags until I leave the store. If Charlie comes
to my house to sell me the stuff, I'm קונה Koneh it
once it's in my house even if it's in Charlie's bags. And
the גמרא Gemara says no, it's really not about whose domain. The
domain really meant whose bags are they in. And we're just assuming
it's the same bags as the owner of the domain. Okay, it's
a very obviously weak read of that ברייתא. Baraita. Dov, you had
a question?
If according to the ברייתא Baraita the domain is קונה. Koneh. Yeah.
So I'm in your store and you put the apples, I just
bought your apples
and you put
the money, you put the apples in my bag. Before I leave
the store, you could be חוזר? Chozer?
Yes, as can you, unless you do הגבהה. Hagbahah. If you do
הגבהה... Hagbahah...
Chasing after me before I step out of the store? Correct. Yeah,
I'm sorry, the
price just...
unless you do הגבהה Hagbahah or שוכר מקומו. Socher mekomo. If you
want to make sure the sale is final.
I've picked up the bag. Picked it up. That's הגבהה. Hagbahah.
Right,
if you want to make sure the sale is final, because let's
say we're not just talking about a few apples, you're buying from
me,
20 bushels of grain in my warehouse, how the heck are you
going to... by the time you get your truck here and move
the whole thing out and you're going to do משיכה, Meshichah, you
want to make the sale final, you give me a penny and
you rent the space that they're on and you're קונה. Koneh. That's
what the משנה Mishna says. אם פיקח הוא שוכר מקומו. Im pikeach
hu socher mekomo. But yes, as long as they're in my domain
and you haven't taken them out or done הגבהה, Hagbahah, either one
of us can be חוזר. Chozer. Correct, the sale is not final.
So a
handshake's
not good?
Well, handshake might be a later קנין. Kinyan. The אחרונים Achronim talk
about something called סיטומתא Sitomta like where there is
an acceptable
norm, that whatever, convention amongst buyers that a certain thing is recognized
as a finalizing of a deal and in those cases that might
actually work as well. Like there might be a certain do-it-yourself type
of a קנין, Kinyan, once it's within convention recognized within the whole
industry. Like people say like in the diamond industry when you say
מזל וברכה, Mazal u'vracha, that means that the deal is final. So
yeah, there's actually a whole discussion about that.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Is that in the category of a person's word? No, that's more
seen in the category similar to that of חליפין, Chalipin, where חליפין
Chalipin is less about representing ownership as just a symbolic act that
shows that the deal is final, that you're completely committed to it.
So the best way to conceptualize that is a type of a
parallel to חליפין. Chalipin. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, so אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so we're still not done.
We still haven't proven one way or another
whether כלים Kelim works ברשות מוכר. Bereshut mocher. תא שמע, Ta shema,
come and hear.
משך, Meshach, now the better גרסא Girsa here is not חמורה Chamora
but חמרין ופועלין Chamarin upoalin הכניסן לתוך ביתו. Hachnisan letoch beito. So
here Charlie still is selling me his apples. They're all in these
bags on his donkeys and I go ahead and
I lead his donkey, now whether it's donkeys or donkey drivers and
his workers and I pull them into my house and they're leading
the donkeys and they're all coming into my house loaded up with
their bags loaded up with their apples. Okay, now that first point
is I did not do משיכה. Meshichah. You might think I did
משיכה, Meshichah, but I did not because I didn't do משיכה Meshichah
on the apples. I only did משיכה Meshichah on the donkeys, not
directly on the apples. Even there there's some discussion in the גמרא
Gemara that if Charlie explicitly says to me do משיכה Meshichah on
my donkey and thereby be קונה Koneh the apples that are on
it, that might work. Okay, but that's not the case here. He
didn't say that explicitly. Not only that, it might be that I'm
just schlepping the donkey drivers and they're the ones that are schlepping
the donkey. So it doesn't count as משיכה. Meshichah. But I've now
brought them into my house. Now think for a minute. They're in
my house but they're on Charlie's donkeys in my house. Okay, now
we are going to assume here's an interesting question that the גמרא
Gemara says... never explicitly addressed, and it doesn't explicitly address here as
well. But even if my חצר chatzer is קונה koneh when they're
in Charlie's bags, they're not קונה koneh when they're on Charlie's donkeys
or on Charlie's workers. Okay, the fact that those are live things
that can move on their own, they're not sort of, you know,
a כלי kli is just sitting there. So you could say my
domain takes over, you know, because it's sitting in my domain. If
it's on a donkey and, you know, I can't my חצר chatzer
won't be קונה koneh the apples on his donkey, they'll be קונה
koneh the apples in his bag maybe, but not in his donkey.
If the bag is put down, but not while they're on the
donkey. So I שלעפּט schlepped these into my domain, it's not משיכה,
meshicha, it's not קנין חצר kinyan chatzer because they're still on the
donkey. Okay, now, בין פסק עד שלא מדד בין מדד עד שלא
פסק, bein pasak ad shelo madad bein madad ad shelo pasak,
whether you establish the price, פסק pasak is like the price per
pound, okay, but you haven't yet measured out the amount, or you
measured it out without establishing the price, it doesn't really or even
if you did both really, it doesn't really matter. שניהם יכולים לחזור
בהן, shneihem yecholim lachzor bahen, either I or Charlie can go back
because there's been no מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, they're still on the
backs of his donkeys. Now, פירקן והכניסן לתוך ביתו, pirkan vehichnisan letoch
beito,
let's say however Charlie unloaded the donkeys, okay, and now the bags
of apples are sitting in my house, okay, and in that case,
after they've been now sort of taken off and they're in the
house, פסק עד שלא מדד, pasak ad shelo madad, okay, oh and
now, so now the קנין kinyan is ready to happen, it's in
my חצר. chatzer. The question is do we have a גמירות דעת?
gemirut da'at? This gets back to the issues of our משנה. mishna.
Okay, so if we've established the price, we've already agreed that I'm
buying all of his apples, and we've established how much per pound.
The only thing we haven't done is we haven't weighed it out
to know how many pounds there are and therefore what the final
bill is. But we've agreed to the amount, I'm buying all of
his apples, and we've agreed to the price per pound. In that
case, פסק עד שלא מדד, pasak ad shelo madad, if you've agreed
to the price even if you haven't measured it, אין שניהם יכולים
לחזור בהן, ein shneihem yecholim lachzor bahen, you can't retract because then
the sale's final. There's a גמירות דעת gemirut da'at and it's in
my yard. מדד עד שלא פסק, madad ad shelo pasak, however, if
we've measured it but we haven't agreed at the price per pound,
so there's no גמירות דעת gemirut da'at yet. I might not agree
to the price Charlie's charging. In that case, שניהם יכולים לחזור בהן.
shneihem yecholim lachzor bahen. Fine. So that's just saying that you need
the גמירות דעת, gemirut da'at, you need to agree to a price,
but you don't need to actually measure it out. Now what you
do see though is as soon as Charlie has unloaded his donkeys
and it's in my yard, I'm קונה, koneh, even though the apples
are in Charlie's bags. So you see you go by חצר chatzer
and not by כלי. kli. So that's what it says. ומה כליו
של מוכר ברשות לוקח לא קנה. uma kelav shel mocher birshut lokeach
lo kana. So for since you see that being in Charlie's vessel
in my domain, now לא קנה lo kana means Charlie isn't קונה,
koneh, means Charlie doesn't retain possession, you see you go by the
רשות, reshut, that's what the lesson of this ברייתא braita is. כליו
של לוקח נמי ברשות מוכר לא קנה. kelav shel lokeach nami birshut
mocher lo kana. So my vessel's in his domain, I won't possess,
you go by the רשות. reshut. You don't go by the כלי,
kli, you go by the רשות. reshut. That seems to be the
clear lesson of this ברייתא. braita. So let's see how the גמרא
Gemara answers it. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק בששפכן. amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak besheshafchan. No, we don't mean that Charlie just unloaded
the bags of his apples, we mean he poured out his apples
and they're sitting straight in my house. So there are no כלים
keilim of Charlie, that's why it works. So איקפיד רבא, ikpid Rava,
רבא Rava who was trying to bring a proof from this ברייתא
braita was offended that that was an answer that was being suggested.
He says מידי שפכן קתני? פירקן קתני. midi shafchan katani? pirkan katani.
It doesn't say he spilled it out, he says he unloaded his
donkey, which means they're still sitting in Charlie's bags and I'm still
קונה. koneh. All right, seems like a very good proof.
אלא אמר מר בר רב אשי במתחלי דתומא. ela amar Mar bar
Rav Ashi bematachli detuma. We're talking about a case of like I
don't know like strings of
garlic. Somehow those were things that weren't kept in bags, those were
hanging loose, okay,
and since they were like now when you buy these garlic you
buy them in these sleeves, okay. So let's assume that when you
sell them you sell them with the sleeves. So Charlie is not
taking the sleeves back. So you had these long sleeves or these
long strings of garlic, yeah braided, right, these long braids of garlic
and he just so therefore they weren't in any bags. You didn't
empty the bags because there weren't bags, it was stuff you were
carrying straight on your donkey's backs without bags. It says I'm קונה?
koneh? So then I'm קונה koneh because it's a חצר. chatzer. But
you can't prove that
חצר chatzer works with them and he put them down? Yeah.
On your floor? Yeah. Okay. So you can't bring this as a
proof about what happens if they're in somebody else's כלי kli because
we're making it a case that there were no bags, okay. Let's
just read one more answer. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
so אמר ליה הונא בריה דמר זוטא לרבינא מכדי פירקן קתני. amar
lei Huna breih deMar Zutra leRavina michdi pirkan katani. No, no, no,
then we're going to go on. So basically so we'll move on.
So we'll worry tomorrow about that question about what the מדד madad
and the פסוק pasuk matter, but again we have a case where
it seems very clear like the תוספתא tosefta that it doesn't matter
about the כלים, keilim, it matters whose domain they're in, and rather
than accept the conclusion, we've said it's a special case where there
are no כלים. keilim. Okay, and we're still trying to argue that
maybe if they still are in the כלים, keilim, it would be
defined by the כלים keilim and not by the domain. Okay, so
to be continued tomorrow. Have a great
day.